你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到PWN学院的内核安全模块
welcome to the kernel security module of pwn college
我是Yan，今天我们要讨论的是
I am Yan and today we're going to be talking about
Linux内核中的shellcode
intricacies of shellcode in the Linux kernel
到目前为止
so far in this course
你做了很多用户空间的事情
you've done a lot of user space stuff
写过了大量的用户空间shellcode
you've written a lot of user space shellcode
其中一些可能看起来像屏幕上的
some of it might look like what you see on the screen
这是一个简单干净的shellcode，打开，读，写，然后退出
that's a simple open read write and then exit cleanly shellcode
整个课程中，你可能一直用它来实现目标
that might be used throughout the course to achieve your goals
当你执行shellcode来泄漏flag时
once you have shellcode execution to leak the flag
这个用户空间的shellcode，不会有效果
now this user space shellcode won't work
如果完全照着这个在内核中执行
if it is exactly verbatim executed in the kernel
为什么没效果
why not
因为它用了系统调用
well because it uses system calls
回忆一下程序交互模块
and if you recall way back when from the program interaction module
我说过系统调用是一个接口
I said that system calls are an interface
让用户空间代码
for user space code
能与运行在0环的内核交互
to interact with kernel that it's running under the supervision
像这样
as such
当syscall指令发生时
when a syscall instruction happens
控制流会跳转到，内核内部的系统调用入口函数
and control flow redirects into the syscall entry function inside the kernel
内核假定它来自用户空间
the kernel assumes that it is coming from user space
控制权之前在用户空间
that control had been in user space
之前在用户空间执行
execution had been in user space
再进入内核的
and then it moved into the kernel
这种假设
this Assumption
导致内核会做出某些行为
leads the kernel to make certain actions
如果是在内核空间调用的，这些行为将是非法的
which are invalid if code execution is coming from kernel space
所以如果你在内核空间触发一个系统调用
so if you trigger a system call from kernel space
内核会崩溃
the kernel will crash
实际上很难
it's actually shockingly hard
既要一个功能完整且安全的系统调用接口
to create a functional and secure syscall interface
还要能从内核内部触发
that can also be triggered from inside the kernel
这本就不是系统调用的初衷
that's just not what a syscall is for
因此，在内核空间的shellcode中使用syscall
so if you do a syscall in your kernel space shellcode
事情不会很顺利
things will not work very well at all
事实上，内核会崩溃
in fact your kernel will crash
准确的说，内核线程会崩溃
or really that kernel thread will crash
对于你的进程
and to your process
看起来就好像syscall触发了段错误
it'll look like your syscall instruction triggered a segmentation fault
这在正常情况下是不应该发生的
which under normal circumstances should never happen
该怎么做呢
so what do you do
你要利用你能在内核中执行代码的事实
well what you do is leverage the fact that you are executing code inside the kernel
你就是内核
you are the kernel
这是一个超乎想象的权力
that's an incredible amount of power
通过内核api，你能做任何你想做的事
and you can do anything you want to do by using kernel APIs to do it
你想做的事，能有很多
what you want to do varies
如果你想提升特权
if you want to escalate privileges of course
如之前课程中讨论的
as discussed in prior lectures
可以执行prepare_kernel_cred和commit_creds内核函数
you want to execute the prepare_kernel_cred and the commit_creds kernel functions
你可能想要逃出seccomp
you want to escape from seccomp
可以修改current_task_struct的
you want to mangle the
thread_info中的相关标志
thread_info security flags or the thread_info flags in general of your current tasks structure
如果你想在用户空间中运行命令
if you want to run a command in user space
你可以调用run_cmd内核API
you want to call the run_cmd Kernel API
这些都不涉及系统调用
none of these involve system calls
它们要么需要你找到当前task_struct
they require you to either find the current task_struct
找出目标成员变量的偏移，正确修改目标变量
and figure out how to offset into it properly and modified properly
要么需要调用这里列出的API函数
or call these API functions listed there
它们都不需要，或者说不能，通过系统调用来完成
none of them require or can be done with system calls
内核api就是正常函数
kernel APIs are normal functions
如何调用内核API
what you do to call a kernel API
只需触发call指令
is you trigger the call instruction
而不是syscall指令
not the syscall instruction
但call什么呢
but what do you call
这里，我写了一个shellcode
if I try to make a shellcode here
调用prepare_kernel_cred
with just a very simple call of prepare_kernel_cred
参数为0
with an argument of zero
这里出了什么问题呢
under the hood what goes wrong
GCC编译这个shellcode时
is that GCC when it compiles this shellcode
当它汇编这个shellcode时
when it assembles the shellcode
它创建了一个要重定位的可执行文件
it creates an executable with a relocation
这个重定位基本就是说
and that relocation basically means
它不知道prepare_kernel_cred在哪里
it doesn't know where prepare_kernel_cred is
不知道它是什么
what it is
当然，如果这是puts
of course if this was puts
可能没问题
it might be fine
实际上，还是有问题
it actually wouldn't be fine
你能让它在可执行程序中没问题
but there are things you could do to make it fine in an executable
但在shellcode中不行
not in shellcode
在shellcode中，你不能仅通过其名称调用函数
in shellcode you can't just call a function by its name
在shellcode运行时
shellcode when it runs
它的运行环境是0和1的数据或指令
it runs in memory in the context of ones and zeros
你需要知道函数在哪里，才能调用它
you need to know where a function is to call it
那么如何找到函数的位置呢
so how do you find where the function is
这取决于KASLR是开还是关
well it varies based on whether KASLR is on or off
如果KASLR关了
if KASLR is off
你可以解析一个内核提供的文件
well you can parse a file that the kernel provides
叫/proc/kallsyms
called /proc/kallsyms
只要你是root
as long as you are root
更具体地说
actually more specifically
只要你有特定权限
as long as you have certain privileges
这个，你在pwn学院的容器化设施中，是没有的
that you don't have inside the containerized infrastructure of pwn college
但你在有漏洞的内核镜像，和你的linux机器上有
but you do inside the vulnerable Vms and on your own Linux box
如果你找到一个相同的系统
if you identify an identical system
理想情况下是相同的硬件
ideally the same hardware
相同的内核版本等等
same kernel version etc etc
配置等等
configuration and so on
比如，在pwn学院题目的练习模式中
and this is for example the practice mode for a challenge in pwn college
你可以使用/proc/kallsyms
you can use the /proc/kallsyms file
读出内核函数的内存地址
to read out the address where in memory where certain kernel API functions are located
或内核导出的任何东西的地址
anything that the kernel exports
如果KASLR开了
if KASLR is on
就麻烦了
you have a bigger problem
类似于用户空间的ASLR
but it's analogous to the problem of ASLR is on in the user space
你得泄露一个地址
you need to leak an address
基于这个地址
and based on that address you need to compute
基于泄露地址与目标地址间的偏移量
based on an offset of what you leaked and what you're interested in
你需要计算出目标地址
you need to compute the address of what you're interested in
但
but
尽管现实世界的系统会开启KASLR
though real world systems will have KASLR on
但KASLR关闭的情况也值得练习
it's also important to practice and learn with KASLR off
你会在这个模块练习它
which you'll be able to do in this module
假设你找到了一个内核API的位置
so let's say you found the location of a kernel API
那下一步呢
what next
下一步你要调用它
well next you have to call it
怎么调用它
how do you call it
不能用syscall指令
well you don't use the syscall instruction
得用call指令
you use the call instruction
内核api就是普通函数
kernel apis are normal functions
不幸的是
unfortunately
普通call指令使用一个32位的相对偏移
a normal call instruction takes a relative 32 bit offset
它会移动给定的偏移量，到那里执行
and it shifts execution by that amount and goes there
如果你知道你的shellcode在哪里
if you know where your shellcode is
并且从它到目标函数的距离，在32位表示范围内
and it's within 32 bits difference of the function you want
你就可以用call
you could use a call instruction
但这很烦
but it's a giant pain in the butt
如果你知道你的目标在哪
if you know where your target is
并且
and
你有它在内存中的绝对地址
you have its absolute location in memory
你可以执行绝对跳转的call
you can just make an absolute call
绝对跳转的call必须直接从
an absolute call has to be in direct
跳转目标必须从寄存器取
it has to go through a register
可以通过把目标地址放入寄存器
and you can accomplish it by putting the address you want to jump to into a register
再调用寄存器，来完成绝对跳转
and then calling that register
这会调用该寄存器指向的函数
which calls the function at the address that the register is pointing to
你可以看到
and you can see
在这里
over here
我把这个call大地址的指令，汇编会怎样
what happens if I try to assemble a call to this giant address
提示：调用的操作数类型不匹配
this says operand type mismatch for call
基本就是说
that basically means hey
这个地址太大了
this is too big
32位装不下
it won't fit into 32 bits
即使能装下
and even if it did
我提供了一个绝对地址
I provided an absolute address
但call真正需要的是一个相对地址
but what call really takes is a relative address
有时这很有用
sometimes this is useful
有时，你可能知道shellcode相对于内核的位置
sometimes you might know where your shellcode is in relation to the kernel
但你不知道它们的绝对地址
but you don't know the absolute addresses of either
但
but
KASLR关着的时候，不是这种情况
this isn't the case for example with KASLR off
或知道内核函数绝对地址的情况下
or in cases where you know the absolute address of a kernel API function
这就是常规的间接实现的直接跳转
and so here is our normal indirect absolute jump
汇编没问题
and it come assembles happily
你可以在shellcode中使用它跳转到这个地址
and you can use that in your shellcode to jump to this address
当然，这是一个毫无意义的地址
this is a nonsensical address of course
你会把它换成你想调用的内核函数地址
which you would replace with your address of the kernel API you're interested in calling
这样我们就可以调用内核函数了
so we are able to call kernel APIs
这样我们就能执行run_cmd
that'll let us execute run_cmd
还是执行prepare_kernel_cred
let us actually prepare_kernel_cred
commit_creds，啥都行
commit_creds everything
执行函数没问题了
you're good to go
除了seccomp
except for with seccomp
seccomp逃逸很棘手
escaping seccomp is tricky
需要寻找和修改
requires finding and modifying structures
内核记录当前进程的对象
that the kernel keeps track of  for the current process
叫current的task_struct对象
the current task struct
幸运的是，内核一直指着这个对象
luckily the kernel points to this struct
因为它也需要找到它
because it also needs to find it
用的GS段寄存器记录它
by using the GS segment register
这些段寄存器的使用方法有点棘手
now these segment registers are a little tricky to interact with
它们比RDI和RSI等通用寄存器难用
they're harder to interact with than general purpose registers like RDI and RSI
当然在C代码中
and of course in C
你不需要考虑这些
you don't have to think about any of this
你直接用current变量就行
you just use the current variable
它是内核中的一个神奇的宏
it's a magic macro inside the kernel
它会找到当前的task_struct对象
that finds you the current task_struct
但如何在shellcode中找到它呢
but how do you do that in your shellcode
当然，你可以浏览内核源代码
well you can crawl through kernel source code
试着去理解内核是怎么做的等等
try to understand how the kernel does it etc etc etc
这对你的精神没好处
that's not gonna be good for your sanity
更好的选择是
what is better for your sanity is
让编译器来做苦工
let the compiler do the hard work
用C代码做你想做的
literally write what you want to do in C
你希望你的shellcode做的
what you want your shellcode to end up doing
用C写出来
write that in C
为要攻击的内核，编译它
build it for the kernel that you want to attack and
这可以在我们的PWN学院基础设施中完成
this can be done in our pwn college infrastructure
用vm build命令，很简单
very easily using the vm build command
然后逆向它，看看它是怎么用汇编写的
and reverse engineer that to see how these actions translate into assembly
然后在你的shellcode中用汇编实现它
and then reimplement that assembly in your shellcode
所以在右边
so on the right here
我做了两件事
I do two things
一种是找到
one is I figure out how to get the address of
current->thread_info.flags变量
the current task_struct thread_info flags variable
的地址
the address of that
以及获取这个TIF_SECCOMP的值
and how to get the value of this TIF_SECCOMP
flags内某bit位的偏移值
the offset into the flags
这个bit表示seccomp是开还是关
that is the one bit that says that seccomp is on or off
还有
and
我写了这个最简单的内核模块
I write this minimized kernel module
我构建了它
I build it
在我们的环境中，这非常容易
super easily in our infrastructure
当然，你也可以在这个环境之外，构建它
but you can of course build this outside of the infrastructure as well
我逆向了构建结果
and I disassemble the results to see what happens
这里是相关的
and here is the relevant thing
这里把值放到rax，函数的返回值
this moves into rax the return value of this function
是GS指向地址的偏移量为0的地方
offset of 0 from the GS the global segment register
你可以直接把它复制到你的shellcode中
and this is something that you can just copy into your shellcode
这是一个有效的x86汇编指令
this is valid x86 assembly that will work
这是控制seccomp的标志的偏移量
this is the value of the offset of the seccomp flag
这是
again that is something
这和构建的目标内核版本有关
that is specific to the version of the kernel that I built this for
但是编译器帮我找出来了
but the compiler figured it out for me
我不需要浏览内核源代码
I didn't have to crawl through source code
我可以把它们组合起来
and I can take that put it together
然后构建我的shellcode
and build my shellcode or
更懒点的话，这很好
you're even lazier which is great
你可以用C写
you can put it together in C
汇编它，再提取出来
assemble it and extract it
要注意的是，调用内核函数
one caveat for calling kernel APIs
这行不通
this won't work
这会创建重定位符，让加载器来解析
what this will do is create relocations which the loader will resolve
等内核模块的加载器
when the kernels module loader
当内核模块加载时
when that kernel module is loaded
它会说，嘿
so it will basically say hey
我要call某个东西
I'm gonna call something
我不知道那是什么
I honestly have no idea what it is
它会call 0
it'll literally do call 0
这会汇编成call下一条指令
which will disassemble to calling the next instruction
在加载时
at load time
它会说，好的，要call
it'll say okay okay that's gonna be calling
prepare_kernel_cred之类的
prepare_kernel_cred or whatever
但在汇编代码上看，这说不通
but in the assembly it won't make any sense
这就是为什么难以
this is actually why it's a little tricky to
用没考虑这种情况的工具，反汇编内核模块
disassemble kernel modules in tools that aren't prepared for these sort of tricks
这包括大多数逆向工具
which is actually most of the reversing tools
这就是
so that's how you figure out
对不起
sorry
这就是找到该结构体地址和布局的方法
that's how you figure out the addresses and the layouts of structures
请先尝试使用C语言
please just try to use C first
看看它做了什么
and then see what it does
拷贝出来
and then steal that
现在
now
你知道如何调用内核api
you know how to call kernel Apis
知道如何修改内核数据结构并找到它们等等
you know how to modify kernel data structures and find them etc
基本上就成了
you're basically done
还有什么会出错呢
what could still go wrong
通常
well oftentimes
在内核漏洞利用时，你需要
you need to in kernel exploitation
在用户空间漏洞利用时
in user space exploitation
你可以执行shellcode
you can hit your shellcode
它打印出flag
it prints out the flag
你不用管后面会怎样
you don't care what happens afterwards
但在内核空间中，你要
in kernel space you do
如果是要提权
if it's a privilege escalation
它只提升当前进程的权限
and it just escalates the current process
调用了commit_creds prepare_kernel_cred 0
by calling commit_creds prepare_kernel_cred 0
这将使当前进程成为root进程
that'll make the current process root
如果这时shellcode崩溃了
if then your shellcode crashes
那该进程会在你用它读出flag前，崩溃
the current process will crash before you can use it to read the flag
因此，你必须干净地退出内核shellcode
so you have to have your kernel shellcode exit cleanly
这是至关重要的
that's critical
一个常见的例子
a common example
如果你劫持了内核要调用的函数指针
if you hijack a function pointer that the kernel called
请让你的shellcode执行起来像个函数
make your shellcode act like a function
完成目标后，记得返回
make it return afterwards
就这些
that's all
如果清理干净了
if it cleans up
要确保，栈正常
it makes sure its stack is not messed up
然后清理干净
and then cleans up properly
让内核可以继续执行
the kernel can continue execution
通常
often times
这里的题目中，这些就够了
this actually is probably all you need for these challenges
但一般情况下
but in the general case
修复环境可能会更复杂
fixing up the environment might be more and more advanced
要点是，内核漏洞利用时
but the point is for kernel exploitation
你要确保
you need to make sure that
shellcode执行完，系统仍能正常工作
the system survives after your shellcode
或不管你做什么
or whatever your payload is done
都要执行必要的行为
taking the actions that is taking
最后
finally
我们谈谈调试
we get to debugging
你的shellcode不可能一次就成功
your shellcode isn't gonna work on the first shot
这没事
that's fine
这不是个问题
that's not a problem
如何调试它
how do you debug it
内核漏洞利用有点棘手
well kernel exploits are a little tricky
大多数内核漏洞
most kernel exploits
因为大多数内核漏洞要从内部触发
because most kernel vulnerabilities are triggerable from the inside
要从用户空间触发
from user space
而不能从网络触发
not from like the network let's say
但大多数攻击都有一个用户空间的程序
but most attacks will have a userspace component
这个用户空间的程序
that userspace component
会将有效载荷注入内核以触发bug
will inject the payload into the kernel to trigger the bug
那么你该调试什么呢
so what do you debug
如果你用gdb调试用户空间的攻击程序
if you run GDB on your user space attack component
在vm镜像中的攻击程序
your attack program inside the VM
这很好也很简单
that's nice and easy
里面会有你攻击程序的所有符号等等
it'll have all the symbols of your attack program etc
但这样，你完全不知道内核中发生了什么
but it leaves you completely completely blind as to what the kernel is doing
这样你不能步入syscall
so you can't single step through system calls
不能进入系统调用
into system calls
不能进入系统调用处理程序
into the handlers
不能进入有漏洞的内核代码
into the vulnerable kernel code
正如我之前提到的
and as I mentioned before
在gdb中调试用户空间的程序，通常的结果是
the typical outcome is from inside GDB debugging your user space component
看起来就像
it'll look like
syscall指令
for example the syscall instruction
触发了段错误，或sigill或sigkill之类的
segfaulted or sigilled or sigkilled or whatever
不管怎样，就崩了
however it gets broken
所以你要做的就是连接到QEMU
so what you have to do is attach to QEMU itself
在GDB之外
outside of GDB
调试内核
to debug your kernel
当然
now of course
如果你没有运行Qemu的话
if you aren't running a Qemu
如果就运行在平常的硬件上
if you're running in actual normal hardware
你可能需要连接
you might have to attach
比如嵌入式设备中，专用的硬件调试器
using a dedicated hardware debugger in an embedded device for example
但在这里
but here
在本模块的练习题中
in the practice challenges of this module
你将在Qemu中运行内核
you'll be running the kernel inside Qemu
在PWN学院的环境中
and in the pwn college dojo
你可以运行一个非常方便的vm debug命令
there's a very handy vm debug command that you can run
它会附加到运行中的内核
and it will attach to the running kernel
现在调试用户空间的部分就难了
now it's harder to debug the user space component
你没有用户空间那部分的符号了
you don't have the symbols of your user space component
尽管你有内核的符号
although you do have the symbols of your kernel
这很有帮助
which is helpful
但是没有用户空间程序的符号
but without the symbols of your user space component
就难以
there's a little bit of a headache
断在你期望的用户空间部件中
in breaking at parts of your user space component that you would expect
我的建议是
my advice
编译用户空间的攻击程序时，关掉位置无关代码选项
turn off position independ code in your user space attack component
这个你可以控制
which you will control
然后断在现在已知的地址
and break in the now known addresses for your attack
所以在GDB中，你可以在那里中断
so that in GDB you can break there
然后步入内核
and step your way into the kernel
然后观察导致你利用失败的bug
and observe the bugs being triggered  and your exploit failing
这样你就能修好它
so that you can fix it
总之
TLDR here
在虚拟机之外运行GDB
run GDB outside of the virtual machine
而不要在虚拟机内部
not inside of the virtual machine
希望这是一个有用的技巧教学
hopefully that was a useful quick dive into the different tricks
能帮助你掌握，成功黑入内核所需的知识
that you will need up your sleeve to successfully hack the kernel
能让你在内核中用shellcode做些事情
to successfully execute shellcode that does something in the kernel
做一些有成效的事情
does something productive
你会在这个模块的题目中得到很多练习
you'll get plenty of practice in our challenges for this module
当然还有PWN学院后面的模块
and of course in the rest of pwn college
祝你好运
good luck